Guide to the Albert Waldo Snoke Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Albert Waldo Snoke papers
1861-1988
1946-1988
MS 1471
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
27.5
(59 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, hospital consultation files, reports, subject files, writings, research material, audiocassettes, and photographs, which document Albert W. Snoke's career in hospital administration and his interest in health care. The papers also include material concerning the career of his wife, Parnie Storey Hamilton Snoke, and the Snoke, Storey, and Hamilton families. The papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection. Albert Waldo Snoke was born in Fort Steilacoom, Washington, in 1907. After receiving a B.S. degree from the University of Washington in 1928, he attended Stanford University Medical School and received his M.D. degree in 1933. In 1936, Snoke joined the staff of the Strong Memorial Hospital, Rochester, New York, and became its assistant director in 1937. Snoke left Rochester in 1946 to assume the directorship of Grace-New Haven Hospital in New Haven, Connecticut. In New Haven he also taught hospital administration at Yale University and oversaw the development of the Yale-New Haven Hospital, serving as its executive director from 1965-1968. From 1969-1973, Snoke worked in Illinois as coordinator of health services and later as acting executive director of the Illinois Comprehensive State Health Planning Agency. In 1987 his book, Hospitals, Health, and People, was published. Snoke died on April 18, 1988.
Snoke, Albert W. (Albert Waldo), 1907-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Albert W. Snoke, 1987, and his estate, 1988.
Scope and Contents
The Albert Snoke Papers document the professional life of a hospital administrator known for his contributions to improved patient care. The papers will be of interest to those studying the history of hospital administration, the development of health care delivery systems, and the growth of community hospitals into research centers affiliated with schools of medicine. Though the files contain references to Snoke's work as executive director of Grace-New Haven Hospital, the vast majority of the records of this period are found in the records of Yale-New Haven Hospital (MS 835) in Manuscripts and Archives. These records also contain Snoke's retrospective notes, in which he explains issues and events documented in the executive director's files in MS 835. Snoke created the notes when contemplating writing a history of the hospital and also in anticipation of transferring his papers to Manuscripts and Archives. He may also have used them in preparing for the oral history interview he gave in 1987 (Series II, folders 184-185).
The Snoke Papers focus on Snoke's participation in professional organizations and his role as a consultant, advisor, and author. They also contain personal papers of Albert Snoke, which document his early interests in scouting and the outdoors, particularly Mount Rainier in Washington. Papers of other members of the Snoke and Storey families are also in these files. They focus on life at Stanford University and in Palo Alto, California, but also include a Civil War diary of Riley Storey.
The diary is the oldest item in the papers; other memorabilia of Thomas and Parnie Storey also dates from the nineteenth century. The bulk of the papers, however, dates from 1946, when Snoke moved from Rochester, New York to New Haven. The papers, which include correspondence, hospital consultation files, reports, subject files, writings, research material, and photographs, are arranged in five series, by record type: General Files, Writings, Topical Files, Personal and Family Papers, and Photographs. Thus material on a particular subject might be found in several series. For instance, those interested in Snoke's years in Illinois would need to look in the General Files for correspondence with and memoranda to Illinois Governor Richard Ogilivie, but they might also look for articles and reports from this period in Writings, background material and notes in Topical Files, and pictorial material in Photographs. The inventory of folder titles includes cross-references which are extensive but not all-inclusive. Unless the cross-reference includes a series number, the citation is to a folder number within the same series.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Waldo Snoke was born in Fort Steilacoom, Washington, on July 19, 1907. Snoke was active in Boy Scouts and attained the rank of Eagle. In 1924 he was part of the United States troop which participated in an international jamboree in Copenhagen, Denmark. After graduating from Puyallup High School, he attended the University of Washington and received a B.S. degree in 1928. Snoke then went to the Stanford University Medical School, where he received his M.D. in 1933. He was a resident in the Stanford University Hospital until 1936. During the summer of 1931, Snoke served as a park ranger in Mount Rainier National Park. While at Stanford, Snoke became acquainted with Parnie Storey, a fellow medical student and the daughter of Parnie and Thomas Storey, the latter being the general director of the school of hygiene and physical education at Stanford. They were married in 1934.
Snoke's residency had been in pediatrics, and he went to the Strong Memorial Hospital, in Rochester, New York, expecting to continue in this field of medicine. In 1937, however, he was offered the position of assistant director of the hospital, under Basil MacLean. Snoke remained in this position through World War II. In 1946, he was asked to become the director of the newly formed Grace-New Haven Hospital. In New Haven, he faced the problems of fusing two medical facilities, their staffs, and budgets, while building a new memorial unit. Snoke was instrumental in balancing the interests and resolving the tensions between the private physicians, who had used the Grace Hospital facilities, and the faculty members of the Yale University Medical School, who had brought their classes to the bedsides of patients in the New Haven Hospital.
Snoke was known for his concern for patient care and for his interest in the role of the university teaching hospital. It was under his influence that the hospital developed the concept of "rooming-in" to allow newborn babies to stay with their mothers in the mother's room. He also developed a training program for hospital administrators and encouraged the improvement of the university's nursing school. Snoke played a major role in the formation of the Yale-New Haven Medical Center, Inc., which raised funds and served as a coordinating structure for the university medical school-hospital partnership.
Snoke was a national leader in hospital administration and was active in professional organizations. He served the American Hospital Association (AHA) in numerous ways, chairing its Councils on Hospital Planning and Plant Operations, on Prepayment Plans and Hospital Reimbursement, and on Professional Practice. He was president of the AHA from 1956-1957 and received the AHA's Distinguished Service Award in 1965. Snoke also served as president of the Connecticut Hospital Association (1954-1955), and was a member of the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals, the Joint Commission on the Improvement of Care of the Patient and the National Commission on Public General Hospitals. He was often called upon as a consultant on hospital operations and worked in partnership with his wife Parnie, who, besides having an M.D., received a degree in public health from Yale in 1961.
For reasons he did not entirely understand, Snoke was forced to resign as executive director of the Yale-New Haven Hospital on December 31, 1967. He was then named the acting executive director of the Illinois Comprehensive State Planning Agency and Coordinator of Health Services under Governor Richard Ogilvie and held this post until 1973. His resignation followed Ogilvie's defeat for reelection. While in Illinois, he helped develop a model Emergency Medical Service and Trauma Program.
Snoke deplored the tendency of health professionals and health institutions to be preoccupied with the business of medicine rather than the care of patients. He sought ways to bring about cooperation between all types of health care institutions to ensure a continuum of care which would include prevention and post-acute care as well as the treatment of acute illness. Snoke spoke out for a national policy for health and welfare. He was active in the formation of health maintenance organizations and supported the creation of the Medicare system. He was also an advocate of the Connecticut Regional Medical Program. In 1987, the Yale University Press published Snoke's Hospitals, Health, and People, containing his reflections on his long career and such contemporary problems as reimbursement and cost containment, patients' inability to pay for medical care, program management, marketing, and corporate organization. Snoke died on April 18, 1988.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. General Files, 1917-1988. II. Writings, 1937-1988. III. Topical Files, 1937-1982. IV. Personal and Family Papers, 1861-1988. V. Photographs, 1907-1988.
Health planning -- Law and legislation -- United States; Hospitals -- Administration; Medical care -- United States; Medical economics -- United States; Medical ethics; Medical policy -- United States; Medicine; National health insurance; Public health; Regional medical programs; Mount Rainier National Park (Wash.); Palo Alto (Calif.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Chapman, Carleton B., 1915-; Clark, Henry T. (Henry Toole), 1917-2008; Crosby, Edwin L. (Edwin Lorenzo), 1908-; Darling, G. B. (George B.); DeNardis, Lawrence Joseph, 1938-; Hague, James E.; Kinzer, David M.; Masur, Jack, 1908-1969; McMahon, John Alexander, 1921-2008; Morrissey, Edward F.; Ogilvie, Richard B.; Rytand, David A.; Snoke, Albert W. (Albert Waldo), 1907-; Snoke, Parnie; Thompson, John; Illinois. Governor (1969-1973: Ogilvie); American Hospital Association; Boy Scouts of America; Carrier Corporation; Commission on Public-General Hospitals; Connecticut Regional Medical Program; Grace-New Haven Community Hospital; Jersey City Medical Center (N.J.); Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals; Kentucky Council on Public Higher Education; Medical Administrators Conference; Society of Medical Administrators (U.S.); Stanford University; Yale-New Haven Medical Center
- General Files, 1917-1988; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The General Files comprise the largest series in the papers. The series includes correspondence, memoranda, notes, agendas, and minutes which document Albert Snoke's professional interests in health care and hospital administration. The General Files also highlight many of Albert Snoke's personal friendships and civic interests, including a life-long interest in the Boy Scouts and service on the board of the Carrier Corporation. The files are arranged by individual or organizational name in alphabetical order. Within each file the materials are arranged chronologically.
  Though the material in these files dates from 1917 to 1988, the bulk of the material dates from after Snoke's resignation as executive director of the Yale-New Haven Medical Center. The earliest files are those for family members, including Snoke's parents, John Waldo and Helen Snoke, his wife, Parnie Snoke, and her parents, Thomas A. and Parnie Storey. Letters to his parents include descriptions of the Boy Scout jamboree in Denmark, while letters to Parnie describe summers spent at Camp Wig-was-ati in Ontario, Canada, during the early 1940s. Files for mentor Basil MacLean and medical friends George Darling, Jack Masur, and David Rytand are also helpful in following Snoke's career. The files for Grace-New Haven Hospital and for Frederick Wiggin supply some information on Snoke's decision to move to New Haven and the evolution of his administration.
  Because Snoke's files as executive director remain in the Yale-New Haven Hospital Records, material in the general files for the period of the late 1940s through the mid 1960s generally concerns Snoke's involvement in professional associations. There are a number of files that document Snoke's work with the American Hospital Association, including his year as president. In addition to the files for the association itself, there are also materials in the files of Edwin Crosby and Alexander McMahon. Snoke's involvement in other professional organizations is recorded in the files for the Commission on Public-General Hospitals, the Connecticut Hospital Association, the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals, the Medical Administrators Conference, and the Society of Medical Administrators.
  In 1968 Snoke was forced to resign from the Yale-New Haven Medical Center. Files which document this difficult period in his career include those for Frederick G. Redlich, Yale University, and the Yale-New Haven Hospital. Snoke's activities in the years following his resignation are well-documented in these files. Numerous files concern Snoke's work in Illinois. Files for Governor Richard Ogilvie contain memoranda and position papers outlining Snoke's duties and his ideas on how health care change should or could be brought about in Illinois. Other important correspondents on the work in Illinois include John Dailey, David Kinzer, and George Lindsley.
  During the 1970s Snoke was involved in various health care initiatives in Connecticut. The files for New Haven Health Care, Inc., the Connecticut Regional Medical Program, Henry T. Clark, Lawrence DeNardis, and Edward Morrissey contain discussions of these activities. There are also files for various clients for whom Snoke served as a consultant, such as the Candler General Hospital, the Detroit General Hospital, the Jersey City Medical Center, the Kentucky Commission on Public Higher Education, the Samaritan Health Service, and the University of Louisville Health Sciences Center.
  In the late 1970s Snoke became interested in plans for a national health care program, and he hoped that a group of colleagues, including John Thompson and Carleton Chapman of the Commonwealth Fund, could publish on this topic. There are mentions of this interest in the files of numerous friends and acquaintances. Eventually Snoke wrote his own book, Health, Hospitals and People. For additional correspondence on this see the files for James Hague and Edward Tripp.
  The files demonstrate Snoke's efforts to stay in contact with former students, such as James Malloy, and many personal friends. Many letters mention planned visits. James L. Collier, Lester Leutweiler, John Manz, Wallace Root, and Burns Roensch were all members of the Boy Scout troop that went to the international Jamboree with Snoke in 1924. As the files document, he maintained a particularly close relationship with them.
  - A-Am (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - An-Az (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aga Kahn IV, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albert, James T., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alway, Robert H., 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Board of Anesthesiology, Inc., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Board of Preventative Medicine and Public Health, 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American College of Hospital Administrators, 1966-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American College of Radiology, 1957-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Hospital Association, 1944-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10-15)
    General note
    See also: folders 106, 121, 143, 254, 257-258
  - American Hospital Association; International Hospital of Congress, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Hospital Association Publishing, Inc., 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    See also: folder 296
  - American Journal of Public Health, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Life League; American Life Lobby, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - American Medical Association, 1952-1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - American Public Health Association, 1968-1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - American Society of Anesthesiologists, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Society of Clinical Pathologists, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - American University of Beirut, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Anderson, Herbert, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Arandal, Otto
    See: folder 196
  - Army War College (United States) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1967-1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    See also: folder 97
  - Australia, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - B-Blac (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Blak-Brac (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brad-By (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Baehr, George, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Bailey, Maurice
    See: folder 193
  - Barkun, Harvey, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Barnett, E. Dwight, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Baylor, James, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Baylor University, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Beahrs, John V., 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Beecher, Henry K., 1952 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Behrent, Ben F., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Belcher, Helen, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Benton, Margaret
    See: folder 323
  - Berger, D. Spencer, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Bernstein, Bernice, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Blackmore, Les and Vera, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Blakney, Richard and Betty, 1968-1987 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Bloomfield, Arthur, 1946-1962 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Bourns, Courtney
    See: Series II, folder 11
  - Boy Scouts of America, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Boy Scouts of America, Mount Rainier Council, 1974-1984 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Boy Scouts of America, National Museum, 1974-1986 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Boyce, Virginia, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Boyd, David R., 1972-1981 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Boyer, Harold
    See: folder 398
  - Bradley, Lawrence J., 1956-1985 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Brann, Lester W., Jr., 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Brennan, Edward T., 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Briggs, John, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - British Columbia, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Brockman, C. Frank and Evelyn, 1956-1986 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Brown, Ray E., 1955-1972 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Brown, Vernon and Madison, 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Burford, Richard B., 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Ca-Cl (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Co-Cu (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - California (state), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Campbell, Robert and Marna, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Candler General Hospital, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    See also: folder 53
  - Caplan, Lewis E. "Bud", 1966-1979 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Carrier Corporation, 1972-1981 (Box 4, Folder 66-67)
  - Catholic Hospital Association, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Cavanagh, Robert F., 1984 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Chapman, Carleton B., 1974-1979 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Chase, Robert A., 1957-1986 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Chicago Hospital Council, 1965-1985 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Cisar, Gayle, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Clark, Henry T., Jr., 1956-1983 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Clay, Clement C., 1946-1972 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Cockeram, Dorothy and Elizabeth Plumb, 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Cohen, Wilbur, 1969-1985 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Cohn, Roy, 1958-1979 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Coleman, Tom; Coleman and Associates, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Collier, James L., 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Commission On Public-General Hospitals, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1973-1987 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    See also: folder 70
  - Cone, Joseph M., 1956-1966 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Conley, William G., 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Connecticut. State Department of Health (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Connecticut Educational Telecommunications Corporation, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    See: folder 181
  - Connecticut Hospital Association, 1950-1976 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Connecticut Hospital Planning Commission, Inc., 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Connecticut Licensed Practical Nurses Association, Inc., 1973 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Connecticut Nurses' Association, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Connecticut Regional Medical Program, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    See also: folders 271-273
  - Connecticut State Medical Society, 1952-1986 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Connecticut State Society of Anesthesiologists, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Cook, James W., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Cook, Lyle E., 1958 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Coombs, Howard A., 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Cooper, John A. D., 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Cooper, Theodore, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Corbett, Thurston and Dorothy, 1983-1987 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Cordes, Donald W., 1954-1985 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Costello, Charles H.
    See: folder 427
  - Cote, Romeo, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Council of State Governments, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Cousin, Jacques
    See: folder 119
  - Cox, Al and Helen, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Craig, Gary, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Creditor, Morton C., 1972-1986 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Crosby, Edwin L., 1961-1985 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Crosby, John B., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Cunningham, Robert M., 1954-1969 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Cuthbertson, Kenneth, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Cutting, Cecil, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Cutting, Windsor, 1954-1972 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Da-Di (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Do-Du (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Dailey, John P., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Daniels, Jeffrey, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Darling, George and Ann, 1946-1988 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - DeNardis, Lawrence, 1975-1985 (Box 6, Folder 117)
    See also: folder 282
  - DeNicola, John, Jr., 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Detroit General Hospital, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 119)
    See also: folder 196
  - Douglas, Paul, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Drake, David F., 1982-1988 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Dude, Paul, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - DuVal, Merlin, 1972-1986 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Dwyer, Hugh, 1981-1987 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - E (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Earle, Paul, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Eastern Kentucky University, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Edwards, Charles C., 1973-1981 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Emerson, Marion and George, 1945-1988 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Endicott, Kenneth M., 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Esselstyn, Lillian, 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Evans, Nelson, 1956-1981 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Everhart, David, 1977-1985 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Ewing, William, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Fa-Fl (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Fo-Fu (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Fabro, J. Alfred, 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Flashner, Bruce, 1969-1972 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Fletcher, Margaret, 1973-1986 (Box 8, Folder 139)
  - Flynn, Thomas and Mary, 1962-1983 (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Foley, Julia, 1981-1987 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Foote, Franklin, 1960-1969 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Foster, Eloise C., 1981-1988 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Foster, John T. and Katherine, 1964-1988 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Francis C. Wood Institute, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - Frankfort Hospital, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - Freymann, John G., 1974-1982 (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - Ga-Go (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - Gr-Gy (Box 8, Folder 149)
  - Garland, L. Henry, 1961-1964 (Box 8, Folder 150)
  - Geetter, Isidore S., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 151)